A Guide to the Richmond YWCA Archives 1893-1980
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Richmond YWCA Archives 1893-1980
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 177
42.6 linear feet
Richmond YWCA
Administrative Information
Access
Case Study files are restricted
Acquisition Information
The collection was a gift from the YWCA of Greater Richmond to the Special Collections and Archives Department on 8 March, 1983.
Biographical/Historical Information
The YWCA is a national and world-wide fellowship of individuals who strive to help girls develop in all areas-- spiritually, emotionally, mentally, and physically. Principles and goals are implemented in their daily interaction with members of the organization, such as building moral character and developing leadership qualities to teach teamwork. Training girls and young women to grow in the knowledge and love of God is another characteristic that the YWCA incorporates in their daily interaction.
Among others in the meeting at St. Paul's Church in Richmond, Mrs. Emily Fairfax Whittle was the primary founder of the YWCA of Greater Richmond in May 16, 1887. Mrs. Whittle and others in the meeting wanted to help the women who left the shelter of their home to seek outside fortune. As a result of the groups concern, the association's purpose was to protect and provide help for those women who left their home. It was not until 1890 when the association was chartered and Mrs. Whittle was the first president. Several years later, the organization strengthened and was therefore to able to buy two connecting houses. The houses accommodated 45 girls with shelter, a friend, and a personal touch to forge in life. By 1906, the name was amended to the Young Womens Christian Association. A progressive era of the association had developed with Hawes as president in 1911. Under her services, the Phyllis Wheatly Branch for colored women was established and they also became affiliated with the National YMCA. Activities continued to touch every type of women throughout the development of the YWCA. Since 1924, they have been a member of the United Givers Fund and many other supportive organizations that help better the nation. By 1932, the association was becoming involved in group programs for girls, such as day camps and Y-teens. In 1950, clubs were originated, such as the city wide club. Current situations that continue to influence the world or the complexities of our modern life are issues the YWCA addresses through programs and meetings.
The records based of the executive directors begin with Mrs. Cromwell in 1947. The last record on file is in 1977 with Mrs. Robinson as executive director. The executive directors position entails keeping an overview of the YWCA on site.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of general files, committee minutes, forms from various camps, scrapbooks, photographs and case studies. The materials cover the period from 1893 to 1980. The majority of the materials in the Executive Director Files are organizations affiliated with the YWCA. Few of the Executive Director Files contain minutes or correspondence from the executive directors branch in Richmond. Activities held on the Richmond premises are documented in the executive director's files. A majority of the Board of Director files are based on board minutes, related information, and the nominating committee files. Materials from the Constitution, History, and Documents files contain revisions of their constitution and bylaws. There are also many documents on the history of the YWCA in Greater Richmond. National documents are included in the files as well, such as national convention documents.
Series I--Executive Director (1947-1977) The YWCA has been active in their community and around the nation. Programs that help individuals and provide fellowship for everyone are common goals of the organizations that are affiliated with the YWCA. The USO, United Service Organization, in 1950-1958 was one of the earliest documented organizations they participated in to help women and girls grow in all areas. In 1951-1957, the YWCA was a member of the Richmond Area Community Chest. Newsletters, legislative matters, and recreation agencies are ways the YWCA contributed as a member of the organization. After the Community Chest changed their name to The United Givers Fund, the YWCA continued as a member from 1962-1967. In 1958, they joined the Recreation and Roundtable and they continued as a member until 1977. The Richmond International Council, from 1964-1971, was another program the YWCA was involved in to help the people of Richmond. The National Interracial Project, from 1945-1956, was documented as one of the earliest projects the YWCA joined. In 1969-1970, the YWCA continued to support anti-racism through a project called Eliminating Racism. Moreover, they became politically involved in many issues that was advocating individual rights. By 1947, the YWCA was a member of The Virginia Child Labor Committee. Their goal was to try to amend the old Virginia Labor Law. Two executive committee minutes that are documented are in 1947 and 1949. The only documented correspondence is in 1952 with Mrs. Dorothy Richardson as the executive director. The first documented executive director is in 1947 with Mrs. Lillie V.Cromwell as the executive director. There were programs that were created from the YWCA and held at the YWCA site, such as the summer youth programs from 1968-1970. The Saturday night dances were also held at the YWCA from 1948-1954. The joint building project for the YWCA and YMCA was discussed and planned from 1947-1957. The types of materials in the folders are pamphlets, papers, newsletters, and bound books with their agendas and finances.
Series II--Board of Directors (1904-1977) The Board of Directors files consists of three main categories- minutes, nominating committee, and general information on the Richmond YWCA. Board of Director files that include general information on the YWCA range from 1904-1977. These documents include information about resignations of employees, the YWCA's philosophies, and insight on the members. The years 1910-1917, 1925, 1929, 1930, and 1931 are not included in the board files. Board of Director's minutes span the years 1919 to 1971 except for the years 1929, 1939, 1949, 1960, 1963, and 1963. The nominating committee suggested names and nominated members for vacancies on the Board of Directors. Records of the nominating committee date from 1936 to 1977 with the following gaps: 1937, 1974, and 1975. A subseries is designated as Annual Reports in the Board of Directors file that consists of all the committee minutes and general reports on the committees. Subseries A consists of the Annual reports from 1893-1977 except for the following years: 1897, 1898, 1902, 1905, 1906, 1907, 1916, 1917, 1918, 1919, 1944, 1960-68, 1972, 1973, and 1975. Annual reports include reports on the committees in the YWCA. Moreover, statistical, narrative, and membership monthly reports are included in the Annual reports. Some Annual reports are in bound books, notebooks, or loose documents. The Index to Committees in the Annual reports are the minutes of committee meetings. From 1960-1968, Annual reports are filed under a different heading called the Departmental reports, but contain the same type of information as the Annual reports of earlier years. Minutes from the Annual report, board, and executive committees are listed in the Index to the Committee. Reports of general and assistant secretaries can also be found in the index files. From 1960-1977 there are yearly booklets of the YWCA's annual searchlights, noting memorable days of that particular year. Moreover, the searchlight booklets include the members on the board, trustees, and short reports on the departments. A service was held each year and the searchlight was used in the service.
Series III-Constitution, History, and Documents (1892-1985). The YWCA of Greater Richmond revised their constitution and by laws many times throughout the year; however the following years are documented: 1929, 1936, 1939, 1947, 1948, 1949, 1951, 1966, 1969, and 1975. Anniversaries were shared and celebrated among members of the YWCA. Pamphlets and documents concerning anniversary celebrations are documented in 1892, 1915, 1939, 1948, and 1962. There are lot of materials on the history of the YWCA in Greater Richmond. Dates, times, and places are documented to show the improvements and advancements of the organization. Layouts of the different branches are also provided in the files. National YWCA information is also included in the files, such as the national conventions. The following years are documented: 1915, 1936, 1946, 1949, 1955, 1969, 1970, and 1976. Annual reports of the national YWCA are documented in 1898 and 1959-61. The meetings were held in Quebec and New York. Moreover, the national YWCA devised a standards study booklet in 1936-1938. Biennial conferences and conventions of the International YWCA are documented in 1897, 1899, 1911, and 1913.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The executive directors files are arranged alpha by subject. The series are arranged alphabetically and then chronologically. Scrapbooks are located in the oversize area with other scrapbooks.
Organization
The collection is arranged in 11 series.
Series I--Executive Director (1947-1977)
Series II--Board of Directors (1904-1977)
Series III--Constitution, History and Documents (1893-1969)
Series IV--Budgets (1922-1977)
Series V--Camps (1932-1970)
Series VI--Case Studies (n.d.) [Restricted]
Series VII--Committees and Programs (1916-1980)
Series VIII--General Files (1933-1980)
Series IX--City Study (n.d.)
Series X--Photographs
Series XI--Scrapbooks
Contents List
- Series I--Executive Director (1947-1977)
  - Associated Agencies: Action Audit-Eliminating Racism 1970-1972 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Associated Agencies: Alpha Kappa Alpha Sority-Janet Ballard 1978 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Associated Agencies: Applications 1947 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Associated Agencies: Association Reviews-Perkins evaluations 1929-1931 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Associated Agencies: Association Review 1972 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Associated Agencies: Association for World Travel Exchange 1955 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Associated Agencies: National Assciation of Social Workers 1956 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Associated Agencies: Race Relations-Advertisement of Quality Service Inc. undated (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Associated Agencies: RAGA: A Study for people sixty years and over 1951 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Associated Agencies: Recreation and Group Work-Executives Roundtable 1958-1962 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Associated Agencies: Recreation and Group Work-Executives Roundtable 1972 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1951 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1952 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1952 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1953 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1954 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1955 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1956 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1957 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1958 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1967 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1968 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1969 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1970 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Richmond Area Community Council 1971 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Bylaws 1961 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - The Voluntary Agency's Role in Community Levership 1962 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Reports 1963 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - North Richmond Recreation Survey 1953 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Executive Directors Roundtable 1968-1970 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Richmond Area Group Workers Association 1948 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Richmond Area Group Workers Association 1950-1951 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Richmond Area Group Workers Association 1952-1956 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Richmond International Council 1964-1968 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Richmond International Council 1969 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Richmond International Council 1970 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Richmond International Council 1971-1972 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Richmond Law Women (Home to where the hurt is: Help for the battered wife) 1977 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Richmond organized against rape-R.O.A.R. 1975-1976 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Richmond National Committee on the Cause and Cure of War 1931 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Richmond Neighborhood Councils: North Richmond Recreation Study 1953 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Richmond Neighborhood Councils: East Richmond Recreation Study 1954 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Richmond Neighborhood Councils: South Richmond Recreation Study 1954 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Richmond Neighborhood Councils: West Richmond Recreation Study 1954 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Richmond Neighborhood Councils: Richmond Recreation Study 1955 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Richmond Neighborhood Councils: Central Recreation Study 1955 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Richmond Peace Council 1933 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Richmond Peace Council 1934 (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Richmond Peace Council 1935 (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Richmond Peace Council March 1936 (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Richmond Peace Council April 1936 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Richmond Peace Council May 1936 (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Richmond Peace Council June 1936 (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Richmond Peace Council July 1936 (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Richmond Peace Council August 1936 (Box-folder 3:22)
  - Richmond Peace Council September 1936 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Richmond Peace Council October 1936 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Richmond Peace Council November 1936 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Richmond Peace Council December 1936 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Richmond Peace Council January 1937 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Richmond Peace Council February 1937 (Box-fodler 4:6)
  - Richmond Peace Council March 1937 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Richmond Peace Council April 1937 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Richmond Peace Council May 1937 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Richmond Peace Council June 1937 (Boxfolder 4:10)
  - Richmond Peace Council July 1937 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Richmond Peace Council August 1937 (Box-foldoer 4:12)
  - Richmond Peace Council September 1937 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Richmond Peace Council October 1937 (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Richmond Peace Council November 1937 (Box-folder 4:15)
  - Richmond Peace Council December 1937 (Box-folder 4:16)
  - Documented and Publicity Material (1) 1935-1937 (Box-folder 4:17)
  - Documented and Publicity Material (2) 1935-1937 (Box-folder 4:18)
  - Documented and Publicity Material (3) 1935-1937 (Box-folder 4:19)
  - Documented and Publicity Material (4) 1935-1937 (Box-folder 4:20)
  - Documented and Publicity Material (5) 1935-1937 (Box-folder 4:21)
  - Documented and Publicity Material (6) 1935-1937 (Box-folder 4:22)
  - Local Publicity Material 1935-1937 (Box-folder 4:23)
  - Mailing Lists 1936-1937 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Mosque Program 1936 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Newspaper clipping undated (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Richmond Recreation Support Fund 1976 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Richmond USO 1950 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Richmond USO 1951 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Richmond USO 1951 (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Richmond USO 1952 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Richmond USO 1953 (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Richmond USO 1954 (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Richmond USO 1955 (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Richmond USO 1956 (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Richmond USO 1957 (Box-folder 5:13)
  - Richmond USO 1958 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Richmond USO 1959 (Box-folder 5:15)
  - Richmond USO 1963-1965 (Box-folder 5:16)
  - Richmond USO 1968-1969 (Box-folder 5:17)
  - Richmond Youth Services Commission-Info undated (Box-folder 5:18-19)
  - Youth Services System Resource Manual 1977 (Box-folder 5:20)
  - Southern Council on International Relations 1939 (Box-folder 5:21)
  - United Nations Association of Richmond 1976 (Box-folder 5:22)
  - Virginia Committee White House Conference on Aging Report 1961 (Box-folder 5:23)
  - Virginia Conference of Social Welfare 1955-1958 (Box-folder 5:24)
  - Virginia Council on Social Welfare 1969-1972 (Box-folder 5:25)
  - Virginia Council on Human Relations-Richmond Chapter 1970 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Virginia Council on State Legislation 1969-1971 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Women in Community Service 1965-1970 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Women Volunteers on Community Relations 1964 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Workers Education 1926-1930 (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Branch: Chamberlayne Parkway, Committee on Administration 1967 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Branch: Chamberlayne Parkway, Committee on Administration 1968 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Branch: Chamberlayne Parkway, Committee on Administration 1969 (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Branch: Chamberlayne Parkway, Committee on Administration 1970 (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Branch: Chamberlayne Parkway, Committee on Administration 1971 (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Branch-Chamberlayne Parkway, By Law Reports 1969 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Branch-Chamberlayne Parkway, Program Service Reports 1969 (Box-folder 6:12)
  - Branch: Phyllis Wheatley Annual Reports 1948 (Box-folder 6:13)
  - Branch: Phyllis Wheatley Committee on Administration 1950-1953 (Box-folder 6:14)
  - Branch: Phyllis Wheatley Committee on Administration 1954 (Box-folder 6:15)
  - Three Bound Books-Agenda 1954-1955 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Three Bound Books-Agenda 1956 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Three Bound Books-Agenda 1957 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Branch: Phyllis Wheatley- Committee on Administration 1955 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Branch: Phyllis Wheatley- Committee on Administration 1956 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Branch: Phyllis Wheatley- Committee on Administration 1957 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Branch: Phyllis Wheatley- Committee on Administration 1958 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Branch: Phyllis Wheatley- Committee on Administration 1959 (Box-folder 7:8)
  - Branch: Phyllis Wheatley- Committee on Administration 1960 (Box-folder 7:9)
  - Branch: Phyllis Wheatley- Committee on Administration 1961 (Box-folder 7:10)
  - Branch: Phyllis Wheatley- Committee on Administration 1962 (Box-folder 7:11)
  - Branch: Phyllis Wheatley- Committee on Administration 1963 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Business and Professional Girls Department 1941-1948 (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Communist Attacks on YMCA and YWCA 1948-1950 (Box-folder 8:3)
  - Correspondence-National Board Community Sections 1967-1971 (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Correspondence: proposed-Charlottesville YWCA 1952 (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Director, executive: Lillie V. Cromwell 1947-1948 (Box-folder 8:6)
  - Director Executive: Brown 1948-1949 (Box-folder 8:7)
  - Director Executive: Richardson 1950-1954 (Box-folder 8:8)
  - Director Executive: Richardson 1955 (Box-folder 8:9)
  - Director Executive: Richardson and Sherffield 1956 (Box-folder 8:10)
  - Director Executive: Sherffield 1957 (Box-folder 8:11)
  - Director Executive: Sherffield 1958-1959 (Box-folder 8:12)
  - Director Executive: Robinson 1976-1977 (Box-folder 8:13)
  - Evaluations-(1-2) Association Review 1972 (Box-folder 9:1-2)
  - Evaluations-Chamberlayne Parkway Study 1969 (Box-folder 9:3)
  - Evaluations-(1-2) Richmond Council of Social Agencies Study of YWCA 1932 (Box-folder 9:4-5)
  - Evaluations-United Way Agency Evaluation 1975 (Box-folder 9:6)
  - Evaluations-United Way Agency Evaluation 1976 (Box-folder 9:7)
  - Executive Committee Minutes 1947 (Box-folder 9:8)
  - Executive Committee-Virginia Child Labor Law 1947 (Box-folder 9:9)
  - Fee Structure Study-Budgeting Programs 1950 (Box-folder 10:1)
  - Fund Raising 1949-1955 (Box-folder 10:2)
  - Highland Springs Community 1955-1956 (Box-folder 10:3)
  - Industrial Playmakers Guild 1935-1941 (Box-folder 10:4)
  - International Leadership Training Project (Project Committee-Mrs. Saka, Turkey) 1953-1955 (Box-folder 10:5)
  - Interracial Matters 1950 (Box-folder 10:6)
  - Job corps-meeting/reports 1967-1969 (Box-folder 10:7)
  - Joint Planning-Health education and Recreation 1943-1948 (Box-folder 10:8)
  - Master File 1939 (Box-folder 10:9)
  - Mental Health Project-Lift Club with Richmond Psychiatric Clinic 1967-1968 (Box-folder 10:10)
  - Mental Health Project-Lift Club with Richmond Psychiatric Clinic 1969 (Box-folder 10:11)
  - Mental Health Project-Lift Club with Richmond Psychiatric Clinic 1970 (Box-folder 10:12)
  - Mental Health Program 1970-1972 (Box-folder 10:13)
  - Minutes-Executive and Advising Committee and Board of Directors 1960-1961 (Box-folder 11:1)
  - Minutes-Executive Board, Advisors, and Consultant and Board of Directors 1962 (Box-folder 11:2)
  - Minutes-Executive Committee and Advising Committee and Board of Directors 1963-1964 (Box-folder 11:3)
  - Minutes-Executive Committee and Board of Directors 1949 (Box-folder 11:4)
  - Model Neighborhood-Summer Camping Project 1971 (Box-folder 11:5)
  - National Board: South Atlantic Field Committee-The manager 1917 (Box-folder 11:6)
  - National Board Southern Region Atlantic Office 1948-1956 (Box-folder 11:7)
  - National Board Southern Region Atlantic Office: Blue Ridge Conference 1954 (Box-folder 11:8)
  - National Board Southern Region Atlantic Office: Student YMCA/YWCA Conference Emory and Henry College 1956 (Box-folder 11:9)
  - National Board Southern Region Atlantic Office: Susan Love 1967-1971 (Box-folder 11:10)
  - National Interracial Project 1945-1946 (Box-folder 12:1)
  - National Regional Staff Visits 1958-1959 (Box-folder 12:2)
  - National YWCA Literacy Project undated (Box-folder 12:3)
  - National YWCA Questionnaire 1945 (Box-folder 12:4)
  - National YWCA Nominating Committee 1950-1954 (Box-folder 12:5)
  - Neighborhood Conference, Norfolk, Va 1956 (Box-folder 12:6)
  - Neighborhood Conference, Richmond, Va 1953 (Box-folder 12:7)
  - Neighborhood Youth Corps 1968 (Box-folder 12:8)
  - Personnel Committee 1930-1932 (Box-folder 12:9)
  - Personnel Committee 1944 (Box-folder 12:10)
  - Personnel Committee: minutes and policies 1936-1937 (Box-folder 12:11)
  - Personnel Committee: minutes and reports of salary 1932-1942 (Box-folder 12:13)
  - Personnel Standards and Recommended Salary Scale 1931-1943 (Box-folder 12:14)
  - Position Clarification Study, Cromwell 1947-1948 (Box-folder 13:1)
  - Report of Lena M. Fanar 1923 (Box-folder 13:2)
  - Retirement Fund (National YWCA) 1976 (Box-folder 13:3)
  - Richmond Council of Women's Organization undated (Box-folder 13:4)
  - Richmond Daily Council, Annual Report 1956 (Box-folder 13:5)
  - Round the World YWCA Reconstruction Fund: Special Gifts Unit, Mrs. Darling, Chairman undated (Box-folder 13:6)
  - Round the World YWCA Reconstruction Fund: Special Gifts Unit undated (Box-folder 13:7)
  - Round the World YWCA Reconstruction Fund: Women's Organizations Office File undated (Box-folder 13:8)
  - Round the World YWCA Reconstruction Fund: Women's Organization undated (Box-folder 13:9)
  - Round the World YWCA Reconstruction Fund: YWCA Family Unit Office File undated (Box-folder 13:10)
  - Saturday Night Dance 1948-1954 (Box-folder 13:11)
  - Bound Book: Somerville Survey 1932 (Box-folder 13:12)
  - Round the World YWCA Reconstruction Fund, Mrs. Pennell, YWCA Family Unit undated (Box-folder 14:1)
  - Service Shares Campaign 1931-1932 (Box-folder 14:2)
  - Service Shares Campaign 1932 (Box-folder 14:3)
  - Setting Up Conference 1950, 1954, 1955 (Box-folder 14:4)
  - Southeast Regional Conference-Richmond 1951 (Box-folder 14:5)
  - Staff Evaluations and Analysis 1941-1948 (Box-folder 14:6)
  - Staff Manual 1937 (Box-folder 14:7)
  - Staff-National Salary Comparisons 1950-1970 (Box-folder 14:8)
  - Staff Office Members Committee 1946-1977 (Box-folder 14:9)
  - Staff Salary Schedules 1944-1947 (Box-folder 15:1)
  - Staff Meetings-City-wide, Programs, Central 1952-1977 (Box-folder 15:2)